Um, hi folks. My name is Kian Clark and
I work for a company called Near Form.
Uh, we're a company headquartered in the
southeast of Ireland, which is where I'm
from. Um, but we have a kind of a global
presence of folk all around the world in
the US, Canada, um, Italy, Ireland, the
UK, Eastern Europe. Um, and we've we
sort of came of age in the era of no.js
as like the backend language of choice
for folk and event driven programming
and so on. Um, and that's sort of been
our bread and butter for the first kind
of decade of the existence of the
company. But of late, we've been kind of
looking at one another and thinking like
what's the next 10 years going to look
like for us and where can we really put
our mark? Um, and something that's
really interested us has been this world
of AI native engineering and you know
what could we do to lean into a really
progressive methodology of build um
using things like specs to move much
quicker. So I wanted to give a little
bit of a background um as to you know
what our experience has been in the last
6 to9 months in this world. Um, starting
out with the how we got here slide. Um,
then talking a little bit about how it's
compared to our world of vibe coding.
Um, and how, you know, why we like specs
so much. Um, we're going to talk a
little bit about unicorns, but we're not
going to talk about technology company
unicorns of billion dollar valuations.
We are literally talking about
four-legged horselike creatures from the
fantasy world. We're going to have a
good time. Uh, then we're going to talk
about how we do spec driven at nearform,
little bit of lessons learned, and some
resources I found really useful as well.
Um, I'm on LinkedIn. I'd love to say I'm
on all the things, but I'm really just
on LinkedIn these days posting about all
this stuff. Feel free to give me a
follow. Um, and so as we think about
this kind of journey, right, coming
from, um, AI assisted all the way up to
this kind of agentic delivery at scale,
I like to think of, you know, companies
enabling the likes of Copilot, um, box
ticked, right? We're doing AI native
engineering. Like, doesn't really work
out that way, right? So the line by line
level assist is not bringing these mass
productivity gains. Um people take it a
step further and they start doing things
with agents and spanning multiple files,
right? And that does bring some
measurable gains, but I think it has a
real ceiling to what you can accomplish
with this sort of um AI AI augmented
workflow using agent mode. And unless
you can bring in some new techniques and
and frameworks, you know, you're going
to run into issues eventually and and
hit a ceiling of what the what the
models can achieve. Then we come to
specdriven development. Um, in my eyes,
that's kind of the state-of-the-art
right now. That's where I'm spending a
lot of time. Um, and I do think the
gains here are quite measurable. I think
it tends to remove that ceiling of what
you can accomplish with with AI models.
Um, [clears throat] and then if we look
across the the horizon to what's, you
know, what's soon to come. So, how do we
scale this up across multiple teams? Um,
and Guy in his keynote talked about this
transition from single player to
multiplayer. I I love that. That's a
great way to look at this. Um, how do we
all collaborate across multiple teams
delivering things using specs and
agents? Um, rather than just running
through a bunch of tasks as a lone
contributor. Um, that's sort of, you
know, where I see what's next, where I
see a lot of the challenges. And from a
lot of the presentations this morning,
it sounds like, you know, most folks are
in violent agreement. This is, you know,
a thing we would love to see more
progress on.
Um, if we look back across the last 3
years, it's hard to believe that
Copilot's been around since June 2022.
That's pretty wild to me. Um, but
another couple of kind of key things
that have happened along the way. Um,
you know, February of this year, we saw
the term vibe coding get coined. So,
we're really, really recent. Like,
what's that? 10 months ago at most. Um,
another couple of kind of things that
felt momentous. Um, you know, cursor
releasing their 1.0 release in June. And
then again like only two weeks ago or so
their 2.0 release coming out. Uh and in
the meantime as well AWS releasing Kirao
some great sessions here today on Kirro.
Probably the first ID in my eyes to
really codify a lot of the techniques of
spec driven driven development into an
interface. Um something I've really
loved to to see. Um but this really like
condensed timeline in the last nine
months like what's going on? There's
something in the water, right? So it's
been great. I wanted to talk about what
a traditional vibe coding flow looks
like while acknowledging the irony of
using the term traditional in a term
that's been around since February. But
such are the rules of you know the world
we live in these days. And before
talking about this I actually wanted to
jump to a live demo and I'm going to use
Kira in vibe coding mode for today's
demo. Can everybody see that? Okay.
And what I'm going to ask for is I want
to build a 3D rendering engine to render
unicorns. I did promise you unicorns uh
in varying configurations in browser and
we're just going to send it on its merry
way because there is nothing like
combining the demo god's anger for a
live demo in the first place with the
non-deterministic output of models.
Right? So we're going to have a good
time or a really bad time. I'm not
really sure. Let's see how this goes. So
we'll let the model go about its merry
way. And what what typically happens
here, right, is we try to oneshot prompt
what it is we want to build. Um, and
eventually that technique yields, you
know, a technique that doesn't really
scale over time. So I want to build a
unicorn rendering engine. The model goes
and does some work. Then I realize,
actually, I forgot a requirement. I'd
like to make the color of the unicorn's
main customizable.
Then I realized that it's building it in
Vue.js, and I don't know Vue.js. I know
React. So I'd like to retool. Could you
please build this in React instead?
Then I realized the model actually
didn't complete one of those
requirements I asked for earlier. So it
put in a stub for changing the color of
the unicorn's mane, but it didn't
actually complete that feature. Then the
model gets stuck, starts iterating. And
what does a model do in vibe coding mode
when it gets stuck? Every single time, I
swear to God, time to retool the test
runner. So it uses justest for running
its tests. It's going to retool to like
the node native test runner or
something. doesn't fix the problem at
hand, but it loves making busy work for
itself, right? Then along the way, you
know, the model added a feature I didn't
ask for, asking it to back out that
change because I didn't really want that
feature right now. And then all of a
sudden, I'm out of tokens.
So, let's see what Kira's been up to in
VI mode. Okay, it looks like it's built
something. Let's see how it looks.
SDT.
Okay.
Okay. I mean, not terrible, but like not
really a unicorn. Kind of looks like one
of those sausage dogs, right? It's okay.
Um, I did have one I prepared earlier as
well. This is like the best part of this
demo, right? Like nondeterministic
outputs. I don't actually know what the
model is going to give me. Sometimes it
comes out upside down. Sometimes it's
lost a leg through a tragic accident.
Um, it's a lot of fun. Here's another
example of what it produced previously.
That to me is a rhinoceros. That's not a
unicorn, but it is fun to to see what
comes up. So, if we were to approach
that problem with specs, right, how
would it look a little bit differently?
And I think with specs, right, much like
with engineers, we tend to do a lot
better when we kind of force ourselves
to decompose the problem, articulate the
why behind what we're trying to
accomplish, uh, and then use that
context when we go to build something,
right? And it turns out models
appreciate that same kind of
methodology.
And so we might say, "Hey, can you help
me draft a PRD for a unicorn building
rendering engine? Stranger things have
happened." Um, it outputs a PRD. We
review the requirements that the model
has generated. We might then decide to
add some very specific descriptions on
how it is you would go about drawing a
unicorn, and I'll show this in a second.
Then we would ask the model to generate
a text spec, an architecture design
document. It's going to codify in that
architecture document. I actually want
to build this in React and not in Vue.
Please use React. That saved me that you
know that that earlier problem by virtue
of having a PRD. We've been forced to
think about the requirements where it's
hallucinated a bunch of requirements
that we don't really need. We can nuke
those out of the PRD and now they're no
longer going to be built. We just have
so much more control over how we steer
the outputs of the model. It does take a
lot longer, like a lot lot longer, but
the results are unquestionably orders of
magnitude better. And so we've got a
product requirements document, we've got
a text spec, we've got the what and the
why, and we've got the how in our text
spec. Now we're going to ask the the
model to generate a backlog. So
decompose our list of requirements plus
our text spec into a series of tasks
that we're going to go after one by one
in separate context windows. And we'll
talk about this more in a second. Um, in
order to yield better better results,
then a developer begins working on task
one, then task two, then task three with
a very tightly honed context window
relevant to that very task. Um, allowing
the model to have much better results.
I'm going to show you what this looks
like in Kira. Uh, let's jump to better
unicorns.
And so,
not sponsored by Kira, by the way, just
like the two. And in here we've got a
requirements doc. And in here I put in a
very specific piece of context about
looks like a unicorn. And here's that
kind of key differentiator. Right? So
defining what a unicorn is to the model
and then forcing it to think like
Minecraft like visuals and primitives
available within 3JS. And don't get too
ambitious. Right? The reality is with a
a vibe coded model building something in
3.js we're not going to be able to make
a really really detailed unicorn. it's
not going to look amazing. So, let's
embrace it and build something a little
more lowfi.
There's a bunch more in the specs here
about requirements for configuring and
so on. That requirements document
resulted in an architecture document
which I actually didn't make any real
changes to sort of agreed with the base
foundations of it. Quite detailed for,
you know, a fairly basic unicorn
rendering engine.
And then it's decomposed that into a
task backlog. And each of those tasks
has just enough context for the model to
be able to complete the task at hand uh
and be successful. So a much better
bounded use of context. And we'll talk
about that again in a second as well.
I'm going to show what it built
here is a specdriven unicorn. Not
perfect, but I would say that is a much
more plausible unicorn, right? It's got
a main. I can change the color of the
main. Kind of comes in rainbows, which
is nice as a default. Change the color
of the body and so on.
So much better than whatever this poor
miscreant is.
Okay.
So what is it that's happening along the
way um that's caused the you know this
methodology to perform so much better.
Right? So we have this sort of
predictability of outputs in what we're
doing and by virtue of being grounded in
the specs the model is producing a much
more deterministic output on our behalf.
there's fewer wasted cycles along the
way trying to retool trying to add
features remove features and so on and
it's also solved for both the
overeagerness problem that problem of
doing things that I didn't even ask for
and also the undercompleteness problem
of not actually completing requirements
I asked for two different ends of the
spectrum right overeagerness versus
undercompleteness but both equally as
much a problem with that sort of
traditional traditional vibe coding
methodology
so by virtue of having our PR define our
requirements and our architecture design
grounding the model and how to build
things and then decomposing those tasks
into a backlog. You know, I think that's
really the crux of solving for that
overcompleteness or indeed
undercompleteness um by giving the mo
the the the model a much better unit of
work in in you know in the form of those
individual tasks that it's completing.
The other thing we've done a much better
job at doing is a much better bounded
context window along the way. So by
combining the PRD, that what and a
little bit of the why with the
architecture document, the how we're
going to build it, that makes for a
decomposed backlog of things to do for
the model that have just the right
amount of information in order to
complete their task. Last but not least,
by grounding the model in that
architecture document, we're no longer
seeing quite as many arbitrary retooling
cycles. So trying to retool from the
just test runner to something else,
right? It's it's just, you know, busy
work for the model.
If we're specifying in our architecture
document, this is the version of a tool
we want to use, you know, we're less
likely to get that type of behavior.
I wanted to talk now about some of the
building blocks of spec driven
development and how we've been doing
specri and ear form. Um first starting
with the framework that we use. So we'll
often use kirao for building. The other
thing that we use a lot is a tool set
called the bad method. Um and we're
working on incorporating into the bad
method some of our own roles as near
form. So people who we have in near form
being represented by a very hypers
specialized role definition with a
series of commands in each role. Um I
saw in in one of the earlier talks you
know people talking about this idea of
specialized roles rather than g
generalist full stack engineering roles
as a direction of travel for a lot of
agentic development tools. And I think
that's something that holds a lot of
promise. So we've codified what it means
to be a technical director or a QA
tester or a backend engineer and so on.
We've also built a series of templates
for what we think a good PRD looks like,
what we think a good architecture
document looks like and so on. So that
forms this sort of framework that we
ship with each of our projects that
we're delivering in a spectrriven
manner. Then if we look at the project
level specs, the things that live within
the project itself, we have the PRD we
talked about earlier, the requirements
dock. So the what or the why. We have
the architecture doc or the design.mmd
as it's called in kirao which is talking
about how we're going to build this. We
have the project constitution as it's
called in spec kit or I suppose you
could view this as synonymous with um
the claw MD file or a cursor rules file.
But essentially like here's a series of
golden rules for how we build software
in this project that I do not want you
as a model to break. Annoyingly it's
called a different thing in every single
IDE. And it'd be great if we could all
centralize on what we're going to call
this, but we'll get there. Uh, last but
not least, then we have that backlog,
the decomposed list of tasks that we're
going to go after. Um, and within that
backlog, we end up with a series of
specs per story. So, each task gets its
own little bit of context. Um, we like
to write a work log, have the agent
write a work log to that story spec
describing what they've done in the
present task. And that means the N plus1
or the next task is able to look at what
was done previously and use that as
context in how to now go about
implementing its feature because very
very very very often that previous story
is going to dictate what the model's
going to do next. Um, last but not
least, we like to rely on a lot of
models in the open source ecosystem, a
lot of modules rather, sorry. And you
know very often as we discover we're
relying on let's say the very latest
cutting edge version of a module that
the foundation model has no knowledge of
and so usage specs with of course our
good friends in Tessle massively helping
out and teaching the model how to use
something like the latest version of
fastify uh or how to use even a very old
module that might not have critical mass
within the foundation model itself. So
to present prevent those hallucinations
from happening along the way.
[clears throat]
Now, this is all well and good within,
you know, a lone contributor or actually
I really like the term from guy's
keynote, single player versus
multiplayer. Maybe I'm going to steal
that term. But the idea of, you know,
most of the tools for doing spectrum
development right now being centered
around that single player mode of
operation is probably the biggest
challenge that we're having right now.
And so that's something we're having to
work to overcome. Here's kind of the
rough plan on how that's going to go.
And it's showing great promise, but I
don't have all the answers just quite
yet. Um so first and foremost you know
the tools are built with the assumption
that you have a lone contributor an
individual contributor driving all of
the stories that have decomposed
in series one by one right that's not
great where we're building out you know
a team of engineers um that might be
much smaller than a traditional team you
know we're no longer having teams of 12
or 15 people building on an agentic
project it might be three or four so
tiny teams but nonetheless it does kind
of need to be more than one
And so the the sort of way to solve for
this in my head is stories scaled out
across multiple contributors working in
parallel. Um but those stories are then
you know decomposed into tasks
associated with that individual
contributor's specialization. So if we
have a team of let's say a front-end
engineer, a backend engineer and a
DevOps engineer um in the in the process
of decomposing that backlog each of the
stories is going to target one unique
area of the architecture be it front
end, back end or DevOps rather than
trying to span the whole code basis of
builds. Um most of the tools right now
tend to assume the role of a full stack
developer that can just do everything.
And I think as we transition more into
these specialized roles, we're going to
somewhat naturally solve for that
problem of being able to to to
collaborate on work. And so what that
will give us is a backlog of tasks that
very nicely map to areas of a codebase
that are less likely to cause merge
conflicts and things to, you know, work
to butt up against one another. And
it'll allow us to scale to multiple
contributors working in parallel. So
rather than having to to work in series
that's that's kind of the the big change
that we see you know needed in our own
framework of how we build things spec
driven is that ability to go parallel
with that comes some challenges. So if
we have multiple individual contributors
working in parallel on tasks all of a
sudden if one of them forgets to commit
you know during the course of their work
the consequences of that are now much
greater because the codebase in the
background is moving along not at the
pace of regular work but at the pace of
an agentic team. So the pace of change
in the codebase if somebody forgets to
commit rebase pull the latest um is far
far greater. So we actually need this
staging gate within our development life
cycle that actually prevents anybody
from moving on without committing
pushing and making sure that everything
is rebased with with master.
Last but not least that backlog being
able to synchronize it with a sort of an
agile management tool like a Jira or a
GitHub issues or linear to give you know
greater transparency into the work of
those agents via MCP connectivity. Um
makes the whole thing just you know
scale up across a broader team much much
better.
couple of lessons along the way that
we've had on some real projects. So
definitely found spec driven as a
methodology fantastic for MVP uh and I
mean true minimum viable product not
prototypes but true MVPs that you're
going to put in the hands of a
stakeholder that you're actually going
to ship as product and get in customers
hands. Um I I think it's a fantastic
build methodology for that and to that
end really really good on green field
projects.
I've struggled to date with large
brownfield projects. Um, some of the
tooling we use has a workflow for
ingesting and building specs that would
allow models to, you know, do great
things on brownfield projects. Um, but
to date, like early early experiments,
not not the best. Um, I have no doubt
that that's something that we'll see
substantial progress in over the next
couple of months. Um, pretty good as
well in modernization. So like being
able to, you know, upgrade, let's say
we're stuck on, I don't know, node 10
and we want to upgrade to node 22.
That's the type of work that's, you
know, sort of toil for a developer. Um,
great great example of having a bunch of
agents go after that task. We've also
found it really useful, and this is an
unusual one, but uh projects that have a
challenging business case. So where it's
kind of tough to stack up the uh the
case for investment and let's say it
takes a team of you know five six months
to build something uh that's not
something a business is willing to
commit to. If we're able to accelerate
those timelines and cut them in half or
even you know a quarter that makes for a
much more viable um business case
provided that they're willing to accept
that this is a very progressive way of
building software and it does not come
without its you know without its risks.
Um but with that caveat, you know,
plenty of businesses are willing to take
on a more otherwise like challenging
thing to go after um using spec driven.
So it's just been like a nice way of
reframing how we think about building
software as well. Um I mentioned, you
know, today we've struggled in
brownfield, struggled in like
proprietary or legacy languages, um
things that the model isn't very good
at, although we have some plans to work
with the folks in Tesla to try and help
with exactly that. um and also actually
not great for simple prototypes. So if
you just want a front-end prototype, the
specd driven workflow is actually quite
a heavyweight thing um for building that
really simple prototype.
So probably better off to use, you know,
some sort of vibe coding tool, be it KO
in vibe mode or bolt new or or whatever.
Um, just out of curiosity, by show of
hands, how many folks here have used a
spec driven ID in the last month? Okay,
more than half. Okay, so I'm I'm not
completely preaching to the converted
here, but many of you already have
experience. If you haven't yet used some
sort of um some sort of specd driven
enabled IDE, there's two tools in
particular that I've really liked of
late. The first is probably Kira is a
great place to start. Um, if you've got
a couple of hours to spare in building
something, you know, with a spec driven
methodology and you want to move
relatively quickly, its user interface
makes it a really, really easy on-ramp
and it's a great place to get started.
If you feel like you've got a couple of
days to devote and you really want to go
deep on this stuff and see what maybe a
little preview of the future might look
like, the BMAD method, which is is an
open source project on GitHub that
installs quite nicely into the likes of
Cloud Code or Cursor, um, is a fantastic
place to start. It does a lot of that
specialized role definition um and
allows you to follow a really detailed
workflow for your your spec driven
methodology
and then a little bit on what the future
might hold here. So I sort of reckon the
hyperparameter race might not be the
path to success here now and what we're
going to see over the next 6 to 12
months. It's probably going to be more
of a refinement of the techniques and
ways that we interact with foundation
models. Um that's what I'm hopeful for.
I've certainly been wrong in the past,
but you know that feels like the
direction of travel right now. I have
great faith in the fact that the best
approximation of what specri development
is going to look like in the future
right now is living in the open source.
I think that's freaking awesome um in
the form of BMAD. And I'm really excited
as well to see this get codified into
Kira back in was it June July um as the
first thing to codify some of these
specriven primitives and even this week
like two days ago Google launching
anti-gravity again a couple of
specdriven things showing up in
anti-gravity as well. So I'm really
excited to see what some of the other
tool vendors do like what's going to
come next as we try to codify some of
these techniques into how we build. Uh
if you're looking to take some of this
further, a couple of resources. Brigetta
Buckler has some fantastic writing on
Martin Fowler's blog on evaluating um
both the kind of methodology of spec
driven and then also some of the tools.
Um well worth checking out some of her
writing. Uh and then we mentioned, you
know, Kira is a great place to get
started if you got a couple of hours to
spare. And if you want to go really
really deep, I would recommend the BMAD
method. Um it's out there on GitHub. You
can install it into your IDE and have a
play around. Um, I don't know how we're
doing on time for questions. Nope, I
think we're done. All right, I will be
around if people want to chat. And thank
you so much for having me. [applause]
[music]
>> [music]